um figure just kind of my enquiries
about you and your background and what
you're doing at the stoah is kind of
what I thought was interesting for the
podcast so maybe we just jump right in
sure and I will I will say I think this
would be good to include in the podcast
that I I'm resistant to be here right
now because I don't want to be in in
that traditional podcast mode I don't
want to be in that place of let's see
like an epistemic Authority and you know
just like oh listen to me you know I
know everything so I wanted like feel
like I feel resistance on that frame and
I don't know how you're even going to
structure this podcast maybe don't even
have that frame but when I feel into
that kind of like the traditional
podcast format I feel that and I want to
say no to that uh-huh yeah well I guess
what I would say to that is that you
know a couple of people that have been
on the show recently namely rich
Bartlett and Sarah Ness who are kind of
just talking about just the power of our
own like sharing what is just real for
us and what's going on and as well as
even just like what Jack Murphy is
talking about of having some kind of
like higher trust higher bandwidth
conversations that aren't based in a
teacher Lee authority or epidemiological
authority I think is something that I'm
definitely trying to curate on the
podcast just in general and in my life
so I super respect your resistance there
and I want to respect that and I
definitely want this to be as totally
conversational and you know where this
can be totally whatever we want it to be
and I eyes what's coming what's coming
up right there
and I've been talking about this I think
at the stoah and then with my daily
journals is that this feeling of
tomorrow it's like you know tomorrow's
like a concept alright and then if you
actually feel that concept I felt since
of that concept that has died for me
tomorrow has died for me well and when
if there's no tomorrow then you know the
logic dictates there's no today or no
yesterday and if you're kind of living
like there's no tomorrow and this
actually got this this idea was put on
my radar or someone on Facebook saying
about their procrastination like means
putting things off er tomorrow but if
there's the concept that s'more doesn't
exist then it stirred like an anti
crafts nation occurs and it's
interesting and that came up because if
you live like there there's a tomorrow
then you have all these hopes and fears
about your projects like what this podge
of this podcast or things you write or
whatever and then there's like subtle
like egoic machinations like I want it
to be a certain way so you
instrumentalize your word in order to
meet that but if you have no tomorrow
you're just talking in the now that's a
good place to be that's a good place to
be
it feels cool that's a good place to be
and I just even as we just begin to talk
I can hear the like the under lying like
the girders of Stoicism in just like
your views there right yeah yeah so tell
me about stoicism in general like I
don't necessarily think that you have to
be the end-all be-all voice for what
this kind of sect of philosophy is but
tell me how you like came across it and
what it you know what's your history
what what drew you to it and what is it
done for you yeah so I hate talking
about stoicism
hate is too strong a word but I dislike
it why is that
Epictetus said that don't explain your
philosophy and body it and you know I
started this stoicism Toronto group here
about three years ago and it quickly
became like the largest oak group in the
world had a big presence a lot of eyes
were on us and I was sort of bored bored
with it to be honest I didn't enjoy it
because the kind of wider stoic
community they they just sort of talk
about stoicism you know it's like
there's like there's only so much you
can talk about and I will talk about
I'll kind of explained it about life for
you for people who were just on being on
board into the whole philosophy but I
feel like this preface is important for
me and yes I got really bored so I
started this other group called the
intellectual Explorers Club which
afforded me to speak more on sort of my
more jazzy intellectual interests I
called it like being a performative
agnostic method act someone else's
reality tunnel as if it were true so not
only you can think what they think but
you feel what they think or feel what
they feel I should say that was a lot of
fun and that kind of gave me a presence
on the internet with some of my musings
on the culture war and whatnot but when
this whole Kovac thing happened I said
you know what let's combine those two
things my stoicism really came online
doing and this is kind of a search
uncertain liminal state so I said you
know let's combine those things and
start the stoah and the stoah stoah poke
alley is where this original Stoics was
Xena gathered around and talked and
people said hey look through the Stoics
and they got that's how they got their
name and I'm viewing the stoah as a
place that's steward it by a stoic me
but not necessarily to talk about
stoicism a practice solecism which will
happen there but a place to go here and
dialogue about what matters most of a
nice edge of this moment so given all
that uh-huh
I'll give sort of if you'd like and give
you like a 101 version of how I hold
stoicism would love that yeah
so kind of the essence of stoicism is
live in accordance with nature another
way I like to frame it but I got this
from Jordan Hall even though he's not a
stoic is being in right relationship
with reality and how they recommend
going about that is to be virtuous live
in virtue and they talk about the four
cardinal virtues just like Christianity
does prudence or practical reason
courage temperance and justice and the
most important one is is practical
reason you know prudence and you know
and that's sort of like they have these
sort of reasoned heuristics I'd call
them like the bed walk bedrock one is
that dichotomy of control radically
focus on what's in your control and
don't concern yourself with what is not
in your control so there's a sort of
like psychological localism happens when
that occurs and other principles like
negative visualization focus on the
worst case scenario come to terms with
it be okay with it and the more that
they love thy fate right so whatever
happens to you act as if you wrote that
in your own life you know if you had God
mode or whatever and so that's sort of
like the kind of skeleton propositional
skeleton of stoicism and the delicious
thing for me it's more of an
entrepreneurial stoic or spiritual
entrepreneurial a spiritual entrepreneur
this realm is that stoicism is a great
philosophy to find itself in this moment
to be discovered and I say this because
like I think like 90% of the tech stoic
literature would disappeared we don't
have access to it we have access to some
of the like the modern Roman Stoics not
modern almost looks but like the Roman
Stoics like Marcus Aurelius Seneca
epictetus but most of the texts we don't
have access to and we don't really know
how they practiced like you know there's
some lineages like Orthodox Christianity
or Buddhist ik traditions where we kind
of know what it looks like still we
don't know what stoicism looks like how
its practice
and we can pretend we know we can like
but know it's time to reinvent it in my
opinion it's time to discover it ask
what it wants from us I love that
there's some things that come up for me
there as you the idea that you would
ruminate on the worst possible scenario
and come to terms with it I'm a
professional action sports athlete and a
paraglide pilot and a Highliner and
that's just something that I've actually
been talking a lot about lately
especially in the midst of all of this
like looming worst-case scenarios is
really taking a hard look at what the
what all the possible outcomes are and I
recently had a friend on the podcast his
name is Matt blank he's a BASE jumper
and a deep thinker and he talked about
levity on the far side of tragedy and
you know that was in relation to
laughing at people who died BASE jumping
pretty much which is like a pretty dark
thing but it's something it's kind of a
levity that base jumpers used to almost
insulate them from the tragedy that
surrounds them at every jump the
potential tragedy that surrounds them at
every jump and so that's just kind of
like one thing that comes up for me that
I see in like the culture that I live in
that is some kind of stoic embodiment
and I totally agree I love the idea that
you don't like to talk about stoicism
because philosophy is something that
ought be embodied not just talked about
and I think that right now we are in a
crisis of virtue signaling and a lack of
virtue
100% and what I like about what you just
said is I noticed people who gravitated
to the stoic group here in Toronto
or people who gravitate to stoicism in
general people from the military people
from like doctors extreme sports
entrepreneurs people who have to deal
with a high level of uncertainty and
they naturally build their stoic muscle
if you will just doing what they're
doing doing their passion right you have
to be stoic at least in that area that
localized area right so imagine your
stoicism in that extreme sport what was
it again it's that was BASE jumping BASE
jumping imagine this ptosis that you
experienced during BASE jumping and then
just globalize it to every aspect of
your life yeah all right and that's why
they say a peer who know that philosophy
is a way of life it's not something that
we talk about or just talk about we
breathe it yeah I totally agree and I
think that that's a really important
concept but at the same time I think
that right now we are you know I think
that a I think that in general people in
this like big nap that we've been taking
since world war ii where everything has
been so good and the garden has been so
fruitful that everyone has been so
relaxed that i think that some of these
concepts that we're talking about are
just completely and totally foreign to
people that philosophy as a practice
philosophy as a intellectual exercise to
begin with is lost on people it's they
just haven't been exposed to it and you
know here we are we're talking about one
small sect of philosophy that has
ancient roots and deep practicality but
people are completely and totally
unfamiliar with even the terminology or
the mental exercise let alone the
embodiment so I think there is an
importance to talking about the
philosophies that we use to to guide the
principles that modify our behaviors
because I think that most people have
been watching Rick and Morty for quite a
while and I think they need to be
exposed to the different ways of
thinking and the even the mental
exercise of using cognition to determine
principle hmm yeah a few things come up
[Music]
let me feel into the the right thread so
are you familiar with my work on the the
culture war no I can send it to you
afterwards it the the basic premise
there is you know the culture war is not
a bipolar affair anymore like it wasn't
the 1990s or appear to be in the 1990s
and how legacy media presents it today
like a left versus right it's what I
called a multipolar war not I call they
just took that term from international
relations and applied it to the culture
or so a multipolar war is there's
multiple reality tunnels multiple
philosophies in the wild politics
fighting each other it's not just left
and right it's all these like social
justice warriors all right manosphere
neo reactionaries black life matters
they all have these different kind of
you know they have ought alliances
they're fighting each other fighting
against one another and so I we dub that
Conor Barnes and I culture war 2.0 and
if you kind of look back in history
anytime there was a multipolar World
Order it was always before a massive war
like World War 1 World War two
they had a multipolar World Order and so
kind of leads to chaos when you have
that like if you have a bipolar order if
it's like us a Soviet Union or if it's
like packs or unipolar is like Pax
Britannica or packets Americana there's
some kind of stability but if there's
multipolar it's like oh you know danger
coming up and I think we're there now
and so why I mentioned this is that we
can go down that threat to the the
danger threat but why I mentioned this
is my postmodern proclivities the
ability to what I said earlier method
act various reality tunnels and to the
point where you can pastor like I'd
illogical Turing test or just feel what
they feel when they believe what they
believe I think that's a very important
skill set to have and why I mentioned
this is that a lot of people get stuck
with the word philosophy all right like
oh I've learned all these uh terms and
concepts and all this shit and then
there's a there's this own virtue
signaling there with philosophers and I
feel this in the modern stoic movement
there's like a pretension they're like
oh I gotta I gotta use these words and
everything a lot of people I noticed are
intimidated by the word philosophy
because their egos are not associated
with philosophizing or the terms that
they use so I'm very comfortable with my
postmodern proclivities is to use
different terms like being real okay
like just being real and that's and it's
I think it's more important to model it
and allow other people to see you model
it like what I'm trying to do right now
so yeah and why I mentioned all that
this is like if we want to like sell
this or scale it up to people who are
watching Rick and Morty and I never
watch that show by her is good I saw
like I had no judgment on it but if we
want to kind of like bring it to other
people then we might have to use
different languages we have to untether
our ego from these these concepts and
then we got to talk to people in a real
way that to me is true philosophy I
think that touches on the rich Bartlett
and Sarah Nass this power of
authenticity in this and honestly it's
something that is really like relatively
new in my life because I feel like for a
long time I have been are a big part of
my intellectual evolution
involved like objective truth just being
like the tip of the spear and the like
the the highest part of the pyramid and
it led me to kind of just discredit
subjective truths from people and from
myself and I think I like dissolved a
big part of myself there and there was a
lot of me that was hidden because of
that and now as we I think we're both
like on all fronts we're seeing that
just like in our embodied experience we
can see how that's important and how
just like being vulnerable and on
authentic even with ourselves even in
our journal is like a powerful tool as
well as like interpersonally and even
like the scientific literature that's
coming out you know Sarah Nass brought
up this study that was done on this
shale oil rig that hired emotional
intelligence and vulnerability training
for their oil rig workers and like the
incidence of fatal accidents went down
like 80 percent on the oil rigs so this
kind of vulnerability and subjective
truth is really becoming a more
mainstream thing in my mind as well as I
see it externally more and more the one
thing that I want to go back to that
you're talking about and I'm not sure
exactly the term that you use a method
something where you are feeling into
like you're putting yourself in the
shoes of someone else's perspective to
understand what they feel with the
worldview that they have what is that
let's talk about that for a minute
sure yeah and I through I recognized I
threw a bunch of crazy terms out there
and a rapid-fire way and I just want to
also say that I'm glad to be here now at
the beginning you recall I said I didn't
want to be here but I'm glad I'm here
and so thank you for the invite yeah to
answer your question about
the method acting thing was it acting
yeah I familiar with method acting the
technique and um I think that I've
actually come across this but I died the
term seems new to me right so it's it's
like a an acting technique where if you
want to really feel the character that
you're playing if you're an actor right
then you you kind of like put yourself
in the motional reality that that actor
is in or that character would be in so
you kind of like I think I've various
techniques I imagine but you kind of
conjure up memories of past times where
you felt that so you can kind of feel it
when you're acting in that role and when
I meet I mean I'm repurposing that for
understanding all these what I call
nomadic tribes like you know these
different kind of philosophies in the
wild so step one in my opinion actually
it could be step two I don't know one of
the steps is having the ability to
articulate their views in a way where
they feel fully understood all right so
that's step one just on a propositional
level right make sure you your map of
their ideas is correspondent to their
map well that's likely true that's like
being able to argue the other side of
the argument right exactly right so
having that capacity is one of the steps
but then the other step is actually sit
and allow those propositions to sink in
and feel how the world feels when you
believe them to be true
right and you can do this exercise with
social justice activists manosphere in
cells whatever and you actually feel
certain things right yeah this is like
going further than just being able to
play devil's advocate but actually like
beginning to embody for at least a
moment the ideology that you're talking
about yes exactly and then if you can do
that then you can speak to them really
speak to them not you
pretend to speak with them and so I
think that is a really important skill
set to have especially in this liminal
space Wow yeah we're stomachs grumbling
right now so I might mute myself yeah
that is such a powerful tool and I think
that it's been like hinted at in our
discourse of like being able to like
open mindedness is being able to like
consider the other point of view and
people tend to do it just as far as they
can like find a crack in it to argue
against it and it's like this it's a
it's a combat technique as opposed to
some kind of way to have a deeper
understanding and a broader view and a
sympathetic a sympathetic discourse
between someone else who has a different
way of thinking and I it just brings me
to something that I've been just
ruminant ruminating on over and over and
over so much lately is just the idea of
fighting just the reality that I see
that is not people using their
intelligence and their cognition and
their words to like move forward but
merely as a way to weaponize their own
opinions at another it is the
lib tard or you know the Lib tardes
versus the Trump supporters it's like
there is none of this embodied
empathetic method acting which
experientially we know method acting to
be something that is so viscerally
powerful like when you watch the movie
Joker and you see Joaquin Phoenix who is
like become someone else it's like
there's something like URI about it
there's something like so powerful and
almost like terrifying that is like this
person has has like sat with another
reality in a way for so long and in such
a profound way that it like has
literally changed them and we've heard
stories from Hollywood who have like you
know stories of like of Jim Carrey when
he's like there's that movie where he
played that other comedian and Andy
Kaufman Andy Kaufman and the story goes
that like during the entire production
he never came out of character and it
was like almost like detrimental to like
a number of his relationships because he
was like so embodied in this other
person's reality that he like became
them so we know experientially that this
kind of being with another person's
emotional reality or their or you know
not just walking in their shoes per se
but actually like kind of like trying to
like look through their eyes and see the
world through their lenses and try to
feel what they would feel if if that
were the case if they had that ideology
and those emotions and those experiences
we know this to be a really powerful
powerful thing and yet we I find us to
be absolutely just mired in conflict
without resolution no desire to have any
kind of resolution only conflict for the
addiction of conflict right I am
optimistic now and
you know I I did an analysis on a lot of
this on that culture war mimetic tribes
and the culture were 2.0 white paper
that I mentioned maybe I can come back
and chat about it but I was thinking
about that like I never really put this
connection together but when I was
writing that white paper and we had this
spreadsheet of like 32 different reality
tunnels like tribes and you know when I
tried my best to feel into each of them
and I did have a mini breakdown on
writing that paper like a mental
breakdown what helped me out of it was a
Robert Anton Wilson he's a mystical
agnostic and it's like I've used sort of
that because a healthy post-modernism
being able to sit and that cognitive
liminal state without running into a
certain narrative out of fear but I also
just what just came to my right now when
you were talking is how potentially my
stoicism afforded me of the ability to
do that without completely losing my
mind or maybe I did lose my mind I don't
know but like you had like the has some
semblance of sanity right like and
there's a that the process of stoicism
if you follow the stoic algorithm if you
will it naturally leads to what
acceptance commitment therapy calls
cognitive diffusion so your thoughts and
your emotions get separated because I
think a lot of problem is you know the
trigger words right and every matter
tribe has sacred values that trigger
them where they're on their left or the
right so everyone's getting triggered
because my read is that their emotional
reality is so enmeshed with their
propositional reality and that's why I
still exert not really in the culture
where I didn't include them on the the
original mimetic tribe list is because
the Stoics not the capacity just kind of
great distance between the two that's
one of the pillars right yeah and what
mike my kind of like criticism i guess i
don't know it's criticism on the modern
stoic movement like my kind of like the
black sheep of the community a little
bit but like that out of the unknown met
a weirdo but like
my I guess but I don't resonate with the
modern stoic community is that I just
feel like they stay there all right they
just kind of create that distance
between of thoughts and then their
motion they stay there but I like the
idea of turning around you know and then
like now that you have that ability to
turn around and build a relationship
with each one of those emotional
realities mmm all right and if you can
build a good relationship with fear love
all that type of stuff and view each
emotional state as a friend trying to
give you advice but having the prudence
to recognize that even though they're a
friend they don't always give the best
advice I'm gonna have a relationship
with each one of those emotional states
then good shit can happen and so this is
why I feel really called to talk about
stoicism I guess or maybe embody it
publicly where I didn't before because
we're living in this ever since Cove it
happened tomorrow has died even though
maybe hasn't died for everyone it kind
of died because no one knows what
tomorrow will bring right now we're
living in this radically uncertain state
and then I think it's gonna keep getting
more liminal it's gonna keep getting
more crazy how can you set a proper goal
in this in this state you know but
confidently like a smart goal how can
you set one and so I feel called to be
stoic publicly in this moment
hence the stoah yeah I think that the
things that you're talking about from
like a psychological standpoint are just
really super healthy and they the idea
that you would separate your emotions
and your thoughts you would separate
your identity from your emotions and
your thoughts all of these things is
just a really healthy groundwork
framework to be able to go through life
that is in its very nature liminal in
its very nature uncertain like which
kind of makes me think you know like the
uncertainty has really come into like
front and center view but the reality of
uncertainty has always been there yeah
yeah I understand yeah it has never it
it has never been anything else than
uncertain like we're all you know you
talk about tomorrow has ceased to exist
for you now but it the certainty of
tomorrow has always been some kind of
illusion some kind of construct yeah and
that's really well put yeah it's just
sort of like this this is a state this
crisis is an opportunity to wake up to
that reality it really is it really is
the other night I did just getting deep
now I had been given this from a really
trusted friend I had been given this
this changa this activated DMT and it
just kind of like I just had it for
months and months and months and I just
like had never really like had the
calling to to kind of go on that journey
but the other night it was just like it
called him he I was out camping by
myself on a mountain and it's just like
kind of called to me and the thing that
you said about where the Stoics stopped
at separating their emotions from their
thoughts where you want to take it a
step further by turning around and build
relationship with those emotions is was
like strangely reminiscent of this
experience that I had this like really
profound feeling that I was like kind of
transported to this plane of
where I could see that my own
perspective had been knocked loose and
had like floated around 180 so that my
own consciousness could then turn around
and see consciousness as a diffuse
property that then the following
profound realization was that everything
is relational like I only exist in
relationship to the tree right there and
my girlfriend and as you talk about how
the you know building these
relationships with different parts of
yourself it reminds me of the the rich
Bartlett the innermost circle of of of
coming into relationship with each part
of yourself yeah 100% and then it's like
being in right relationship with each
part of yourself because we're always in
a relationship but you know the
relationship could be pathological all
too often Oh to off yeah yeah and it's
sort of like that's going back to the
bedrock of Stoicism you know being right
relationship with reality boom right and
then then you've got to be in right
relationship with everything else if
you're in right relationship with
reality that's why it's like you know
when you're doing your your your extreme
sports it's like you're in right
relationship if you're not gonna die
with it you're gonna be a right
relationship with reality while you're
doing it all right yeah absolutely again
like just globalize that to every aspect
of your life that is philosophy mm-hm
and you know as you say that being in
right relationship with reality or the
first thing that you said was living
within relationship with nature or being
living in accordance with nature as to
how the Stoics originally worded it okay
perfect and that my my girlfriend is an
Ayurvedic practitioner and Ayurveda is
essentially living in and in right
relationship with nature the the rhythms
of your body the rhythms of the seasons
the the seasonal foods all these
different things
and there's like this you know this is
the Zen idea that the truth is actually
this like unnameable it's like this
unnameable you can't even you can't name
it you can only say what it isn't
or you can only like point to it and so
right your example of what the Stoics
say and then a slight variation is what
Greenhalgh says and then like a
variation is what is what I ate a says
about it and then my own personal
anecdote is like like as I do extreme
sports like in a paraglider I'm flying
deep in the mountains like if I just
have some illusory concept it doesn't
actually map on to reality like my life
is literally in danger like I died from
that kind of shit so being in right
relationship with reality is like I feel
like that is a that is pretty close to
pointing at like the ultimate truth like
the right relationship to to reality
right and you yeah go ahead
yeah it's um what's coming up right
there like you know the finger and the
moon type metaphor that you're just kind
of like gesture towards yeah and I feel
that too and I was baptized as a
Orthodox Christian and Orthodox
Christianity there-there pan in theistic
so there's pantheistic which is like a
reality is God and pan in theistic is
reality is God is reality in outside of
reality right and so when I was baptized
in that religion and was brought up I
wasn't really brought up in it it was
like you know my babushka and my grandma
you know like there was a sense that I
was always swimming in reality right and
their goal Orthodox Christianity is
theosis unification with God right which
is very similar with stoicism my
becoming right relationship with reality
right so it's like kind of recognizing
the intimacy there with reality with God
or wherever kind of metaphysics you want
to use and again my postmodern
proclivities allows me to kind of
with both depending who I talk to and
and one thing I think is so critical and
Jordan Peterson talks about this too is
a truthfulness being truthful and my
issue an issue I shouldn't say this with
I guess more accurate sin my annoyance
with atheistic types especially the new
atheist types and a lot of the modern
stoic movement they're all new atheists
sort of LARPing as Stoics and that's
that's that's my uncheered able I'll
throw some shade out there so I get some
heat from it and see how that goes
charitable interpretation of a lot of
them and hold on I just have to say it
again they are new atheist LARPing as
Stoics that's just too good I hope you
die I kind of didn't want you to repeat
it again I just wanted like disappeared
now that's gonna be like the pig or the
title of the I wanna make a meme out of
it but it's do it there's even though I
confess there's an uncharitable element
there and that uncharitable niskanen
Uyen sigh have so I'll gladly take the
heat and hopefully some productive
conversations will emerge from this but
the well I brought that up is that what
I find a lot of people in the atheistic
community especially the new atheist
communities they really almost like
obsessed with truth right this concept
of truth and the way I hold how they
hold it to be a good performative
agnostic here is that what philosophers
call the correspondence theory of truth
so you have models of reality and if
your models of reality map over and are
accurate to reality then you arrive at
the truth and the best way to do that is
the scientific method
make sure the study is replicated and
you can memorize in institutions and
pass multiple-choice tests and whatnot
all right oh so that that's sort of like
the truth that's a little different than
truthfulness what someone like Peterson
is talking about truthfulness is the
constant act of mapping your words to
what you believe to be true in the
moment that includes your thoughts
includes your emotional reality uh you
know and then I started this whole thing
being truthful great like I don't want
to be here that was that was a truthful
thing
said it and I could tell it maybe you
felt a little bit what the fuck is this
guy and then with and it kind of lends
the delicious conversation it did but it
felt real right and and that is even
though I I think the truth net
correspondence to your truth is
important like I'm not disabusing that I
love science you know like I think
science is important but what I'm
talking to we're talking about what my
jam is what I think people really have
to ground themselves in is this
truthfulness muscle because that
truthfulness muscle keeps you loyal
right keeps you like keeps you loyal
with reality keeps you in right
relationship with reality because then
when you get that egoic machinations
start emerging then you can a bullshit
you're gonna lie gonna try to engineer
shit but when you're truthful yours in
the moment just saying whatever wants to
be said and that is how I think one
maintains right relationship with
reality
hmm yeah it sounds to me like there's
it's almost it's almost synonymous with
the vulnerability of like just speaking
what is actually real for you in the
moment right and that's like a kind of
the parallel that comes up for me there
and I love that idea I think there's
also there's like a parallel virtue that
runs along with that that is humility
that is like that the knowingness of the
the egoic machinations that you're
talking about these like mechanisms that
arise to posture to position to like the
game theoretical part of our nature
however condition that is um yeah go
ahead yeah and all these like kind of
like oh I'll be Huff continued my I'm
charitable is like all these let's sort
of like intellectual nerds where they're
just there's a feeling if you kind of
sink into it there's like a feeling of
knowingness right there's a feeling of
knowingness and there's a certain
quality to knowingness there's a certain
quality to unknowingness and if you
really ground yourself for that
truthfulness muscle you can confidently
be live in that
and I think that's important because we
don't know shit right now it's like
Socrates is going back to Socrates you
know like the only thing I know is I
know nothing yeah yeah and I think it's
important honestly like I think that the
the the truthfulness versus true
delineation I think I'll just make here
quickly for those who aren't familiar
with it I think that it's like if you
are lost driving and you stop and you
ask someone for directions if they
misunderstand you or if they honestly
don't know but they give you their best
interpretation of the directions that
you're asking for and they say yeah just
take your right there and then your
second left and you'll you'll see it
they could be wrong objectively wrong
but could be being truthful they could
be saying what they genuinely think is
true right versus the actual directions
being true and you can be both true and
truthful simultaneously but the this
idea of truthfulness as a muscle as a
practice of vulnerability that is
something that honestly I feel like I'm
a beginner at and I'm practicing it I'm
practicing it just like as much as I can
and had a he a beautiful reaction
yesterday as I had an interaction with
my friend who I literally back spaced me
giving advice and I just told her how I
was feeling and she just like melted
yeah and you know this idea of
vulnerability and our own truthfulness I
really feel is at it is a cornerstone of
this mimetic war that you're talking
about I think that in the culture war in
the mimetic war there is so much
posturing and bullshit that is this
pretending of knowing this regurgitation
of someone else who they thought had
authority so they just
educate the authority but in reality
there's no knowing there's no humility
there's no you know there's no method
acting that has gone in to the other
side of it and it's just this this back
and forth warfare based in some kind of
addiction for warfare and I think
there's another element that is almost
the disillusionment that through their
own knowingness air quotes knowingness
or certainty they can somehow dispel the
uncertainty and the liminality of life
itself mm-hmm
yeah there's like arrogance there is
this like it there's everyone is like
putting on this mask right and Sarah
Ness and I talked about what that looks
like in leadership because I don't know
if you saw Eric Weinstein his talk with
Danish Martin burger but or with that
it's on Joe Rogan and and Eric says that
that the the the responsible speech that
needs to be made by world leaders right
now is I am so sorry I just need to
apologize to everyone I didn't prepare
for this in accordance with the academic
papers and I you know I I didn't take
the necessary precautions and we're all
gonna pay for that so I need your
apologies I'm gonna resign immediately
and I'm gonna hand it over to someone
who's in the blah blah blah
but the reality is that all of our
leaders have to put on this mask that
pretends that they're infallible that
they did everything right that they
cannot admit any mistakes and what I
talked about with Sarah Ness is that
there's this negative feedback loop that
the people the citizens are not prepared
to hear a vulnerable truthful mistake
ridden speech from a world leader right
and this is I drew the parallel to our
medical system where
the patients are looking for a pill for
an ill and the doctors get stuck in this
loop so the doctors are then like
they're up against a wall to tell their
patients that no you're gonna need a
stop drinking coca-cola and stop doing
this you're gonna need to walk eight
miles a day you're gonna need to like
leave your friends group you're gonna
need to get a new job you have to move
you have like the list of holistic
realities that need to go into having
such a physical transformation as is
necessary so often here in our modern
world it's like we I think in some ways
stoicism really lends itself to being
able to like pull off your mask be real
with what is happening in you so that
you can even begin to comprehend the
truthfulness that could come down the
hill from someone above you in some kind
of any kind of hierarchy really because
I feel like we have lost our ability to
to hear from authority that they have
made a mistake that they don't know
what's going on but they're not sure
what to do yes we're like allergic to
the uncertainty Peter yeah like I would
I really liked what you said is that
metaphor you use it with the map someone
comes with direction that is perfect as
you know the map territory thing and
your hundred-percent right is like
someone can be really truthful but there
it got it wrong right and that's why you
kind of need everyone to be truthful
because that is when the truth will come
out the truth will be some s in a way
right if everyone starts opening up
their eyes and just kind of risks being
truthful with the blind men and the
elephant then that I start opening up
and we can say you the elephant
collectively but we have to talk to each
other truthfully and for some reason
Trump is coming to mind because there is
an odd authentic see he's an oddly
authentic in a way yeah because it's
like he's the king of bullshit but he
bullshit's in such a way where it's kind
of like he winks at you at the same time
like yeah you know I'm bullshitting and
I know you know right and then there's
like his feeling you feel him he's
really authentic there and so I do
think he got elected for a reason
because I think people felt that
authenticity and I think that could be a
good step towards leaders who are as
authentic as that but truthful at the
same time so I think there's a hunger
here and I think Trump is just sort of
maybe a step towards that direction to
be nationally charitable that brings up
a couple things for me that I've been
thinking about lately and Eric Weinstein
again brought up this amazing point that
he years ago wrote this article I think
he refers to it as K fab and it's this
idea that like in professional wrestling
like in professional wrestling the
outcomes are known before the match
starts
but like the death rate of the wrestlers
is like very real like these guys are
like getting broken collar bones and
scapula's at every match and like all
these like there is a real element to it
but in general the entire thing though
is a fabrication right and we are
hopefully fingers crossed we are moments
away from our political structures being
seen for what they are where the there
are real elements to it but the
framework itself the rivalry the
outcomes are for the most part
fabricated right and he talks about I
don't know have you ever seen the clip
but Donald Trump has literally been
involved in professional wrestling like
yeah oh yeah I saw yeah right he had
this match with Vince McMahon who is the
founder of the WWE and Weinstein like
talks about how powerful Donald Trump is
because he Intuit's he into its
professional wrestling and he into its
this
this underlying thing that is that goes
back to like Vince McMahon basically in
the history of the WWE they basically
got pulled into Congress because they
were about to face this huge spike in
taxes because they were being they were
being
like they were falling into the category
of sports and sports has a whole nother
tax bracket that they have to pay into
and Vince McMahon goes in to the
congressional hearing and he basically
pulls the mask off the whole thing and
he says that the entire thing is made up
which at the time it would like this was
like a trade secret and he went in there
and said this entire thing is made up
we are not sports you cannot tax us like
this and what happened to professional
wrestling did the whole thing
disintegrate no it didn't fucking
disintegrate at all it like if if
nothing else it got more popular and so
this for me is if something is something
that I'm not sure actually how to feel
about this
it's something that I've that I've
intuited for a long time that people in
general kind of know that the whole
thing is made up and that what we're
doing on the internet seems to be
something that we are like talking about
totally different things and no matter
how concretely we dispel some of the
myths that are in the the gated
institutional narrative no matter how
like victorious we are in dispelling
some of those myths the gated
institutional narrative does not respond
at all it's like we know that the
wrestling is fake but the that the
wrestling doesn't stop it doesn't change
it at all and it doesn't stop people
from watching or listening or being a
fan or any of this stuff so um I'll say
this as closing thoughts because I have
to eat something I'm so hungry yeah I
like that so a couple things came up
like the transparent bullshit right well
maybe when bullshit becomes transparent
is is an opening an existential opening
there and and I'm not too worried about
the institutional gatekeepers
John Rafiki said something when he came
to the stoah it's like we gotta steal
the culture right and it being a good
thief it's like you just take you know
why play a game that's corrupt right let
them do what they want lose our own game
and I think we're in a moment an
opportunity here to go back to
truthfulness and I mentioned this
previously about this the word
apocalypse a lot of people talk about
apocalypse means those on the internet
and the etymology of apocalypse is to
disclose reveal uncover well the only
way we can do that is if we become
truthful if we speak our truth if we lie
bullshit you know keep the merit of
existing based off fear or the multiple
narratives we run into them that's
that's that's inspired by fear then you
know we're gonna compromise our
truthfulness but if we really want that
collective truth to emerge we want to
summon it then it's our responsibility
to be truthful in this moment
collectively together I think that's the
only way through this and there's a fork
really a heaven in hell fork to get all
you know Christian on our ass and it's
up to us right now to be truthful and
model it and inspire other people to do
it
and I think that's the only way to come
out of this on the on a positive on the
positive side I love that Peter and I
think that's a great closing thought
really appreciate your time here I
appreciate what you're doing over at the
stoah I'm stoked to be a part of it and
yeah I really appreciate it man
yeah man thanks for having me okay let's
talk to him all right